Joey Chiao-Yin Hsiao

jcyhsiao@umich.edu • +1 (734) 730-0963 • http://joeyhsiao.info

4365 N. Quad, 105 S. State St., Ann Arbor, MI 48109, USA

CV Last Update: June, 2021

RESEARCH INTEREST

I am a mixed-method HCI researcher with strong qualitative and quantitative research skills. My dissertation research focuses on improving inclusive design to support recent immigrants' online networking, online trust, and engagement in consumer-to-consumer (C2C) e-commerce. In addition to my dissertation research, I have employed a wide range of research techniques to tackle research questions in domains such as email behavior, sharing economy, and on-body user interfaces.

EDUCATION

University of Michigan

Ann Arbor, MI, USA

Ph.D in Information

09/2015 - 08/2021 (anticipated)

Advisor: Dr. Tawanna R. Dillahunt National Taiwan University

Taipei, Taiwan

M.S. in Computer Science

09/2010 - 06/2013

Advisor: Dr. Jane Yung-Jen Hsu

Carnegie Mellon University (Silicon Valley Campus)

Moffett Field, CA, USA

Visiting Student

07/2012 - 09/2012

Advisor: Dr. Ted Selker National Taiwan University

Taipei, Taiwan

B.S. in Computer Science

09/2006 - 06/2010

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCES

UX Research & Consumer Insights Team, Verizon Media

Sunnyvale, CA, USA

Academic Research Collaborator (Remote)

09/2020 - 01/2021

Extended the internship research project by finishing up the project and contributing the results as an academic research article (research manager: Frank Bentley)

UX Research Intern (Remote)

06/2020 - 08/2020

Led a project on exploring email-inspired information needs by conducting a series of studies, which included a two-week diary study, semi-structured interviews, and multiple online surveys (research manager: Frank Bentley)

Social Innovations Group, School of Information, Univ. of Michigan

Ann Arbor, MI, USA

Graduate Student Research Assistant

09/2015 – present

Lead research projects of the Social Innovations Group (SIG), which are focused on designing technologies to help low-resourced populations seek employment and education (Advisor: Dr. Tawanna R. Dillahunt)

UX Team, Intel-NTU IoX Center

Taipei, Taiwan

Research Assistant

07/2014 - 07/2015

Carried out research on user experience and natural user interface under smart environment as the only M.S. member in the team (Advisor: Dr. Bing-Yu Chen)

Workshop Organizer

03/2015 - 05/2015

Organized the collaborative workshop on design thinking of Stanford d.school and National Taiwan University IoX Center

Collaborative & Social Computing Lab, Dept. CS, Natl. Tsing-Hua Univ.

Hsinchu, Taiwan

Visiting Research Assistant

07/2014 - 07/2015

Led a project on friendsourcing, aiming to understand how social capital works when a SNS user requests resources on her/his own social network (Advisor: Dr. Hao-Chuan Wang)

Intelligent Agents Lab, Dept. CSIE, Natl. Taiwan Univ.

Taipei, Taiwan

03/2011 - 07/2013

System Administrator
Managed devices and web services for 30+ lab members

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-Reviewed Journal Articles

[J1] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. and Dillahunt, T. R. (2018). Technology to Support Immigrant Access to Social Capital and Adaptation to a New Country. *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction*, Vol. 2, CSCW, Article 70. (acceptance rate: 25.6%).

PUBLICATIONS (Cont.)

Peer-Reviewed Conference Proceeding Papers

- [C8] Cherubini, M., Lu, A. J., Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Zhao, M., Aggarwal, A., and Dillahunt, T. R. (2021). Elucidating Skills for Job Seekers: Insights and Critical Concerns from a Field Deployment in Switzerland. In *Proc. of the 2021 ACM Designing Interactive Systems conference (DIS '21)*.
- [C7] Dillahunt, T. R., Israni A., Lu, A. J., Cai, M., and Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2021). Examining the Use of Online Platforms for Employment: A Survey of US Job Seekers. In *Proc. of the 2021 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '21)* (acceptance rate: 26.3%).
- [C6] Dillahunt, T. R. and Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2021). SkillsIdentifier: A Tool to Promote Career Identity and Self-efficacy Among Underrepresented Job Seekers. In *Proc. of The Annual Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences (HICSS '21)* (Presenter).
- [C5] Dillahunt, T. R. and Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2020). Positive Feedback and Self-reflection: Features to Support Self-efficacy among Underrepresented Job Seekers. To appear in *Proc. of The ACM CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems 2020 (CHI '20)* (acceptance rate: 24.3%; Presenter).
- [C4] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Moser, C., Schoenebeck, S., and Dillahunt, T. R. (2018). The Role of Demographics, Trust, Computer Self-efficacy, and Ease of Use in the Sharing Economy. In *Proc. of the 1st ACM SIGCAS Conference on Computing and Sustainable Societies (COMPASS '18)*, Article 37 (Presenter).
- [C3] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., and Dillahunt, T. R. (2017). People-Nearby Applications: How Newcomers Move Their Relationships Offline and Develop Social and Cultural Capital. In *Proc. of the 2017 ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW '17)*, 26-40 (acceptance rate: 33%; Presenter).
- [C2] Rajan, R., Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Lahoti, D., and Selker, T. (2013). "Roger that!" The Value of Adding Social Feedback in Audio-mediated Communications. In *Proc. of IFIP TC.13 International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction 2013 (INTERACT '13)*, 471-488 (acceptance rate: 31%).
- [C1] Tsai, W.-C., Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Lee, H.-C., Huang, C.-H., Hu, J.-C., Liang, R.-H., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2013). Designing a Reminiscence Aid in Personal Soundscape. In *Proc. of International Association of Societies of Design Research 2013 (IASDR '13)*, 5150-5160.

Posters, Workshop Papers, and Presentations

- [P9] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. and Dillahunt, T. R. (2021) More than Shared Ethnicity: Shared Identity's Role in Transnational Newcomers' Trust in Local Consumer-to-Consumer E-commerce. In *The ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems Extended Abstract 2021 (CHI EA '21)* (Presenter).
- [P8] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2019) Fostering Immigrants' Trust in Online Local Social Exchange. Presented at The 22nd ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW '19), Doctoral Consortium (Presenter).
- [P7] Haimson, O. L., Semaan, B., Dym, B., Hsiao, J. C.-Y, Herron, D., and Moncur, W. (2019) Life Transitions and Social Technologies: Research and Design for Times of Life Change. Workshop at *The 22nd ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW '19)*.
- [P6] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Dillahunt, T. R. (2017) Detecting Life Changes: Increasing Opportunities to Benefit from People-Nearby Applications. In Proc. of *The ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems Extended Abstract 2017 (CHI EA '17)*, 1700 1707 (Presenter).
- [P5] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Pan, M.-H., Wang, H.-C., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2015) Let's Solve It Together: Introducing Crowd Workers to Friendsourcing for Improving Creative Design. Presented at *The Taiwan Computer-Human Interaction Workshop 2015 (Tai-CHI '15)* (Presenter).
- [P4] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Pan, M.-H., Wang, H.-C., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2015). The Price of the Priceless: Understanding Estimated Costs of Work in Friendsourcing. In *The ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems Extended Abstract 2015 (CHI EA '15)*, 1893-1898 (Presenter).
- [P3] Tsai, W.-C., Lee, H.-C., Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Liang, R.-H., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2013). Framing Design of Reminiscence Aids with Transactive Memory Theory. In *The ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems Extended Abstract 2013 (CHI EA '13)*, 331-336.

PUBLICATIONS (Cont.)

[P2] Tsai, W.-C., Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Lee, H.-C., Huang, C.-H., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2012). In Search of Lost Sounds: Designing a Reminiscence Aid in Everyday Soundscape. Presented at *The ACM conference on Designing Interactive Systems 2012 (DIS '12)*.

[P1] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Jih, W.-R., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2012). Recognizing Continuous Social Engagement Level in Dyadic Conversation by Using Turn-taking and Speech Emotion Patterns. Presented at AAAI '12 Activity Context Representation Workshop (ACR '12) (Presenter).

Unpublished Theses and Research Reports

[U3] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2018). Social Network Matters: Opportunities for Technologies to Support Immigrants' Jobseeking. Field Prelim, School of Information, Univ. of Michigan.

[U2] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2017). Can People-Nearby Applications Benefit Newly-Arrived Immigrants? An Exploratory Study. *Pre-candidacy research paper*, School of Information, Univ. of Michigan.

[U1] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2012). Assessing Engagement in Conversation by Hierarchically Decomposing Emotion and Interaction. *Master's Thesis*, Dept. of Computer Science and Information Engineering (CSIE), Natl. Taiwan Univ.

RESEARCH PROJECTS

Exploring Information Needs Sparked by Email

Research Leader (as an Intern)

Summer 2021

Exploring email-inspired information needs by conducting a series of mixed-method field studies, which included a two-week diary study with 50 participants, and three online surveys with 500+ respondents.

Designing Next-Generational Employment Tools for Underserved Job Seekers

Research Leader Fall 2018 - Present

Designing, deploying, and investigating novel employment tools' influences on resource-constrained job seekers' job search.

Designing Social Technologies to Support Newly Arrived Immigrants' Adaptation

Research Leader Summer 2016 - Present

Exploring socio-technical factors that affect recent immigrants' engagement in using social applications to interact with ethnically mixed user communities, and designing technology interventions that address these factors.

Investigating Factors Influencing Participation in the Sharing Economy

Research Assistant

Fall 2017 - Spring 2018

Examining the effects of online trust, demographics, and digital literacy on people's participating in the digital sharing economy.

Discovering People-Nearby Applications' Potential Benefits for People who Face Life Transitions

Research Leader

Fall 2015 - Spring 2016

Studying how people who are new to an area use people-nearby applications' (PNAs) to develop social capital and what are the concerns associated to their use.

HONORS

University of Michigan

Ann Arbor, MI, USA

Rackham Candidate Research Grant

2021

Was granted \$3,000 for conducting research on the project that explores immigrants' social technology use for adaptation.

Graham Sustainability Institute, University of Michigan

Ann Arbor, MI, USA

Dow Sustainability Doctoral Fellowship

2020

Was granted \$15,000 for research on designing social technologies to support immigrants' adaptation and local communities' sustainability; Only ten UM doctoral candidates were granted with the fellowship.

University of Michigan

Ann Arbor, MI, USA

Rackham Pre-candidate Research Grant

2016

Was granted \$1,500 for conducting research on the project that explores immigrants' social technology use for adaptation.

PROFESSIONAL SERVICES Professional Events & Activities ACM MobileHCI 2019 09/2017 - 10/2019Student Volunteer Chair 01/2015 - 07/2015Taiwan CHI 2015 Organizing Committee OpenHCI Workshop 2014 (student-organized workshop on HCI in Taiwan) 01/2014 - 07/2014Steering Committee OpenHCI Workshop 2013 01/2013 - 07/2013Program Chair OpenHCI Workshop 2011 01/2011 - 07/2011Registration and Volunteer Chair Social Events & Activities Univ. of Michigan, School of Information 08/2018 - 07/2019 Doctoral Committee - Student Representative First Taiwan Night at CSCW 2019 Organizing Committee Annual Taiwan Night at CHI 2015 - 2018 Organizing Committee **Mandatory Military Service** Taiwan

Company Chief Consultant (Second Lieutenant)

2013 - 2014

07/2011

Handled psychological consulting, human resources management, and welfare of a military company with 40+ members

Peer Reviewer

ACM CHI 2017 - 2021; ACM CSCW 2017 - 2021; ACM DIS 2021; ACM MobileHCI 2018 & 2019; ACM TEI 2017

Conference Student Volunteer

ACM CSCW 2018, 2019; ACM COMPASS 2018; ACM CHI 2017

TE

EACHING EXPERIENCE	
Teaching Assistant/Graduate Student Instructor School of Information, Univ. of Michigan SI-622: Usability Testing Instructor: Prof. Joyojeet Pal	Winter 2018
School of Information, Univ. of Michigan SI-501: Contextual Inquiry Instructor: Prof. Kentaro Toyama	Fall 2017
Dept. CSIE, Natl. Taiwan Univ. & Dept. Design, Natl. Taiwan Univ. of Tech. and Sci. Advanced Human-Computer Interface/User-Oriented Innovation Design Instructor: Prof. Hsien-Hui Tang & Prof. Mike Y. Chen	Spring 2013
Dept. CSIE, Natl. Taiwan Univ. Introduction to Computer Science Instructor: Prof. Jane Yung-Jen Hsu	Fall 2011
Student Coach	

SPEAKING ENGAGEMENT

OpenHCI Workshop 2011

Invited Speaker	School of Information, Univ. of Michigan
SI699: Mastery User Experience Research and Design	12/2019
Lightning Speaker	Univ. of Michigan
iDEI: Talks at the Intersection of Information, Diversity, Equ	uity & Inclusion 10/2018